Okay.
We are going to go ahead and get started.
I would like to introduce Jack Wotherspoon from Google.
He is working on the Gemini CLI.
And he's going to be talking about the war of our generation.
Okay.
Actually forget I said that he's going to be talking about humans versus slop.
Forget I said that. Thank you very much, Jack.
Round of applause.
Thank you, thank you.
Macy.
Notes a jam packed day.
So thank you all for coming.
We've heard throughout this today.
You know, AI is becoming so much more popular.
You're changing tools every few weeks.
There's always new models coming out.
Things are changing and evolving so fast.
Today we're going to talk about open source,
how something that has kind of had social contract and worked
the same way for a really long time, has started to have a parallel
parallelized shift towards like AI and how we perceive open source
so quickly.
What we'll cover, we'll cover kind of the old world.
We'll set the stage for what open source was.
Then we'll talk into how AI is changing that.
I use the word slop, but I don't actually really like that word too much.
AI generated code is changing open source, whether it's for the better
or for the worst.
We'll get into that one second.
There we go.
And then we'll talk about the new rules.
So how you can navigate open source properly
now that AI is really there's no longer a human connection potentially.
You used to always know when you were in open source,
someone put up a pull request or created an issue.
There's a real user on the end.
Now we're shifting towards you're not sure if that's Claude,
if that's someone's bot, if that's someone's agent.
So we'll get back to what open source
has been traditionally, it's kind of had a human to human experience.
It's been a way where people can come together
as a community, build software, learn from one another.
So kind of what I mentioned is normally back a few years ago,
you were an open source maintainer or working in open source.
You would expect if you see an issue created, that's a real user who's
running into an actual issue
that you should probably take a look at, and every pull, request or code
that was put up to your repository was by someone who probably thought about it
was actually handwriting code, and there was a social contract.
So if you were an external contributor to an open source project,
you're kind of expected to read the docs, make sure that whatever is breaking
isn't on your fault.
It's actually the library or the framework that you are using,
and you actually take a look at the code
base, understand why something's going wrong.
Before you would put up kind of a pull request, you'd do some design.
Maybe you would respond to a code review with the user,
go back from the maintainer,
adjust feedback, and kind of iterate, and for them the maintainers side.
The other side of the coin, you're providing guidance.
You're kind of teaching people.
There's kind of a contract there to kind of do mentorship or help people
merge quality work into the project.
So that's no longer really the case.
Or we're seeing an uprise in AI and things are changing.
Like I said, you don't know whether or not that pull request is being put up
by someone's agent, whether they've even actually looked at the code.
Any human eyes have been on that code generated.
And that's because the rise of agents and there are so many different
agents, there's dozens more.
And agents are now becoming really good at long running tasks,
so they can actually use Claude running 24/7.
Recently there's everyone's been really crazed with /go,
where you can essentially just run your agent for a really, really long time.
People are running them for days on end.
And so code.
The other kind of problem here is that code is essentially free.
You know, it's just a prompt away.
You can type something in and you've got code generated in seconds.
And these plans
that are offered by all of the major companies are quite subsidized.
So you're paying $20 or $200, but you're potentially getting
thousands of dollars actual inference out of those subscriptions.
So as the end user, you're not necessarily thinking about the dollar amount.
When you're prompting all these agents, you kind of feel like
you have unlimited resources,
so you can just throw something at it and see if it works.
And here's a really good example of this, where actually, I think starting today,
GitHub copilot has changed from a subscription base
to actually paying for the tokens that you use.
And Theo, one of the tech influencers, actually
showed kind of not an exploit, but actually using the subsidized system
kind of against it, where actually GitHub Copilot measured things in requests.
They didn't actually count tokens, so it was just prompts.
So if you actually trained or had your agent
running for a super, super, super long time,
you could get thousands of dollars worth out of a $20, $30 plan.
So in the case here, a single prompt did over 60 million in tokens,
which would regularly be $200 if you were paying for the actual API cost.
So from a $30 plan, theoretically, you would have been able
to get over $30,000 worth of inference.
So I believe starting today, they've changed this.
So don't go home and try this.
It should no longer work.
You've tried it.
Okay, okay. That's good timing.
That's good timing.
So AI generated code is now abundant.
You've probably heard this before.
It doesn't even matter if you're really technical in background.
My mom, who just got a smartphone only a few years ago,
she could probably figure out
how to actually get something up and get code generated.
So that's kind of where we're at.
So how do we start to put guardrails in effect on projects?
And here's an example.
You could just say to your agent fix all the issues on this repo.
And then it would just start throwing up pull requests
generating thousands and thousands of lines of code.
And really the human you don't have to think about it.
There's no cost zero accountability, which opens up another can of worms.
So here's an example I work for for Google as a developer advocate.
I've been in open source for the past five years at Google, working on Google
ADK, so Agent Development Kit and most recently Gemini CLI.
And here's kind of just an example of some of the pull requests that we see
where you have absolutely gibberish in the actual title.
They we have pull request templates that we expect to try
to help guide how you should be putting up code changes to the repository.
They didn't fill any of them in.
And if you look in the top right corner it's over 30,000 lines of code changed.
So that is not going to pass the test.
And so here's a quick example
of how quickly you can actually go ahead and just spin up an agent.
We're going to say create.
This is Gemini CLI, one of our products.
And we'll say create ten sub agents in parallel to go ahead
and just create nonsensical pull requests to this repository.
And we'll quickly see how in a matter of about 30, 45
seconds, we're going to have ten pull requests up against this repository.
We didn't say what features to build.
It's just going to make up random stuff.
So you can see it's making a culinary slop.
Chef we've got a bribe laundering engineer I have no idea what that is.
And then it's going to go ahead and actually start
putting up these pull requests.
So this is kind of the open source world that we've now come to.
Right? People can throw things.
They can just absolutely create pull requests at a whim.
So how do as maintainers, as stewards
of the open source community, how do we fight this?
So we'll let that run for a few seconds, and then we'll prove that there are ten
pull requests up.
So really this
comes down to maintaining code isn't free.
Generating code is free like we talked about, but maintaining it is not.
And that's really kind of where this battle is now being fought.
So GitHub release that over 45 million pull requests were merged
per month in 2025.
Like we said, how fast AI is evolving this number is probably,
you know, super, super out of date.
I think last I heard, GitHub has been in the news
a lot recently for like trying to keep up with the pace of AI
and all the code generated.
I think last month they said it was over 200 million pull requests.
So we're already seeing five x right there.
And so this leads to a lot of issues.
We've seen multiple different companies already starting to face this.
So curl actually had a basically a swarm of AI agents and bots creating
fake security reports to the point where they were actually getting
flagged by all of the systems and caused them a ton of headache.
We've seen other companies
put in their contributions in their open source repositories
that they just will not take anything that is pure AI generated.
So 100% generated.
And then there's also closed external pull requests.
So essentially it's gotten so bad that they've just said
we're doing it ourselves. We're not going to take anything.
And then ghosty is an interesting one which has this
based system which we'll talk about a bit more in a few minutes.
So what are the main issues?
Breaking down the barriers with AI should be a win, right?
Makes it easier for people to contribute to these projects.
But what's the flip side.
And this is one that I've seen a lot and it's the drive by PR, right?
So you have you run using a library or a framework or whatever
it may be, and something doesn't go wrong.
You say, oh, I've got the error message.
Let me just go and fix this.
You know, I know it's an open source project.
Let me go and contribute to this.
So you just throw in your stack trace,
you clone the repository and ask your agent to fix it.
So that takes like 30s on your end.
But the trick side and we'll assume that this is actually good code generated.
We'll assume that for this scenario.
Then you've got the maintainer who actually has to go and review that.
So they're going to take their time, at least at Google.
We still kind of hand review each PR that goes in.
We have like code reviews that are automated.
And we'll review the code agent first, but then it still gets to a point
where a maintainer looks at the code and ships it
with all the security vulnerabilities and everything.
Right now that has been at scale, we make sure that humans see everything.
So then they go and they post some feedback,
you know, hey, maybe you change these two things and
the drive by
PR really is someone prompted it, but they had no expectation
that they were actually going to have to follow up or do anything.
Right.
So it might have been a good first judgment being like, hey,
I can try to fix this, but they're not going to come back.
So you just have a prompt and forget it.
Where now it's either the maintainer needs to come and kind of take over that
pull request, and it just kind of floats away into the abyss.
The second one is agents like we showed in that quick example of ten sub agents.
It's super easy to paralyze work.
Unfortunately, we have not figured out how to do that as humans
for our own brains, so we might be able to create code super, super fast.
But the burden on the maintainer if we spin up ten pull requests in a minute.
It's not going to take 10s to review all that code generated.
So there's a disconnect there.
And trust is somewhat breaking down.
Like I mentioned, you don't necessarily know whether or not
a human is on the other side of that code, whether it was even looked at.
So when someone puts up a pull request, normally you would have gone back
and forth, hey, why did you make this design decision nowadays?
I don't know when I told me to or Claude told me to.
So now the thing is not actually trust there.
You can't actually assume that whoever put up that code even knows
what's going on.
So what can we do now?
What are the new rules of open source?
And how can we kind of fight these issues.
And again, this will be kind of our experience on how
we actually implement things for Gemini CLI, one of our open source repositories
with 100,000 GitHub stars and over 700 external contributors.
So quite a big scale. We see a lot of this stuff.
The first one is actually pretty trivial.
It's that we require you to put up a issue first before
you can put up a pull request.
So this kind of eliminates 90% of those drive by
where, hey, I'm just going to try to fix this, put up a pull request.
And then we actually close that and say, hey, can you put up an issue first?
So right there, if this is an agent or someone's bot,
they're not going to come back.
And most of the time will not go ahead and create that issue.
Whereas if you're a human on the other side,
you know, you are actually going to take the time to maybe go and file
that and then start working on it, and then we'll take a look at your PR.
So open the issue.
And we normally try to have a maintainer approve that.
Like if it's something that's going to be pretty hefty we'll go back and forth.
Hey what are you thinking on the design okay.
That looks good.
Go ahead and start working on that.
And that solves about probably 90% of the issues right there.
That drive by PR is now kind of eliminated.
There's kind of a buy in for that pull request.
If they're going to put that up.
They've kind of done their work, done their due diligence.
The second one is kind of rate limit contributions.
So for external contributors, we actually kind of put limits on
how many pull requests they can have active at any given time.
So for that example we showed where we just started
generating ten different nonsensical ones.
This would actually get stopped by that.
And it's pretty easy to do in GitHub actions.
But luckily just recently GitHub
actually is now rolling out this feature by default.
So you can actually go into your GitHub repository settings
and actually set a limit for external contributors
to how many active pull requests they can have any given time.
And regular maintainers
or people who are allowed to contribute to the project are not affected by this.
So it's kind of a nice way where you don't, you know, go to sleep
at night, wake up the next morning and be like, oh, I've got 40.
You know, people trying to rewrite an entire library overnight.
And the next one is automation.
If there's going to be automation for generating the code,
you should probably implement automation to help fight that.
And this can be done in a way where you're not not necessarily
even using AI, right.
It can just be through GitHub actions.
So we have some on our repository where it actually will check to see, hey,
we followed up with somebody. Have they responded?
If not after 60 days, which is probably a little generous,
it'll go ahead and actually close out that issue.
So a way of flagging things as stale or not really active.
There's not the buy in on the other side because it is a two way street.
And then some more examples or what you can do to kind of help fight.
This is check in context files into your repository,
and agents are supposed to read instructions
whether they actually read the instructions.
That's a different ball game. But we can do our best.
And so the thing I'll also say is
don't just put into into the repository.
Don't just commit the context files for cloud.
If you're using Claude, that's perfect.
But you should actually add an agent as well.
Because even if
your team is using cloud for development, there might be people who are, you know,
there's so many different tools out there that they might be using
a different tool for development.
So by putting in the other context files in there as well, or through a symlink,
you can actually kind of make
sure that the contributions of everyone are kind of uplifted and get better.
And really it's pretty simple.
You just throw in there like run the tests, follow the PR template.
That's a big one, and it's actually makes quite a big difference.
And you've heard
a lot, I think about this over these two days about agent skills.
Everyone is big on the skills right now.
They're kind of blowing up everywhere.
And they can also really help, not just uplift the quality from AI,
but also from human people as well.
So in our repository, we have a bunch of different skills
that actually help kind of take this drive by or one off
contributors and really raise the bar
so they can actually help get their work merged.
I think the biggest one I personally like a lot is the PR creator.
You basically just say, hey,
create a PR for this, it's going to go look at the template, make sure it's
looking at the code that's changed, run the tests and do all that formatting.
So if someone who is also contributing to the project says, hey,
put up a pull request, it'll go through those exact same steps
that normally someone, a human or maintainer would also do.
It's kind of codifying those skills that you as a human would do
into the code base.
The other one is for docs.
Nobody likes writing docs, but they are so important, especially,
you know, to train the models and to actually have the models kind of
look at the docs is a really big uplift and skill.
So of course we have a docs writer skill to enforce the style guide and make sure
that any features or code that's getting changed has docs going with it.
Code review I'll skip over, but there's a lot of others
and really checking these into the repositories
so that not only your team members get the benefits,
but also external folks is a really good skill.
And we'll take an example of just kind of what this looks like.
So here's a PR of mine actually that's gone through the PR creator skill.
I also have my own personal skill that will like use playwright
to take videos
and screenshots of code changes as well so that you can actually have visual,
visual proof.
I find as a maintainer,
if I see a screenshot or a video in a pull request, it's in my brain already.
Hire a higher level of easier to see the code that's changed,
as well as kind of somewhat knowing that there's been thought into it.
So that's a little bit of what we've been doing at Google in our repositories.
But what are others doing in the open source community?
Let's take a look.
Raise of hands that anyone heard of open
source vacation as as a concept. No.
Okay. Okay.
So it is essentially think about it.
When you go out of office, you probably put in
like an automated email that says, hey, I'll be back at this day two weeks.
Or if you really need something urgent, follow up with my boss.
It's kind of the same concept, but for an open source project,
if the team has a conference like this and we're all going to it,
we can put it into our code base and essentially any pull requests
or issues during that time, we'll get automatically closed and say, hey,
you can put the message saying, hey,
we're on vacation, we're on open source vacation.
It's also another way that open source maintainers,
if you're a solo maintainer and you're actually going out of office,
you can do the same thing so that when you get back from your trip,
you're not automatically swarmed with hundreds of pull requests or issues.
So it's a really cool way to basically say,
hey, we're not accepting contributions right now.
We're coming back in like two days.
And you can configure it to
have the exact message as well as when it ends.
And the Pi coding agent Mario over there has been a big user of this.
He actually will go on really extended periods of OSS
even when he's not not not out of office, but
just doesn't want to accept any new contributions and essentially
be able to get through the backlog, bring it down to zero and then he'll open.
Open it up and gets flooded with more things and then vouch.
Has anyone heard of vouch?
Okay a few if you have heard of vouch.
So vouch is a system for open source.
That's kind of a referral system.
So if someone's trying to get a job, they say, hey, I know Jack.
He can vouch for me.
It's the same concept, but for open source.
So trusted maintainers or contributors can vouch for other people
and essentially say, you know, hey, I know Macy is a good worker.
She's done good code. I'm going to vouch for her.
Now. She can put up pull requests and contribute to the project,
and you can set the system defaults for like unknown people who are new.
So maybe they have some permissions,
but once you get a vouch, you have more access.
And then the flip side you can actually get denounced.
So bots or people who have put up sloppy code
can get denounced denounced, and then they get blocked.
And that's kind of similar to the OS.
It uses markdown.
This uses a TD file.
So you just check it into your repo GitHub actions will scan it.
And essentially is just a list of the GitHub handles
where there's a list for the bad people, a list for the good people.
So stay off the naughty list.
And this is from Mitchell Hashimoto.
So he created ghosty.
He was also one of the founders of Terraform and HashiCorp.
So he's been using it in ghosty,
which is a pretty big open source library for a few months.
And what's actually surprising to me is he said
PR quality has gone way up by the voucher system,
but he actually is still seeing the PR, so it's really just filtering out
the bad ones so that he can get more of the good ones merged in.
So I find that pretty interesting.
This is, this is I haven't swung all the way to this side of the,
of the, of the aisle yet.
But some people are saying, you know, just don't accept issues at all.
And now prompts are the new pull requests.
So don't give me the code.
Just give me the prompt that you use to generate the code
and I'll go do it myself.
So give me all the details.
I need to basically go and fix this.
I haven't swung all the way there yet.
I think that's a little bit harsh, but it is being used by several
big companies out there.
So don't don't give me the output, give me the intent behind it.
And we heard that in the keynote this morning.
You know, it's moving on to intent and context.
So give me the context. Give me the intent.
And if it's right I will go and generate that code using your prompt.
So where do we go from here?
I think there's kind of like a new playbook that we're seeing evolved.
Nobody really knows.
We haven't really settled on. People are trying different things.
There's vouch, there's open source vacation, different automations.
Some people are even just leaving open source because of AI and many bots.
But I think there's kind of a new playbook being written.
And for us, at least for maintainers, it's, you know, create issues.
First, try to set up external contribution limits
so that you can kind of filter out the noise, you know, add the context
and skills to kind of uplift all of the agents out there and then try
these other systems like automation and trust through vouch.
And on the flip side for the contributors, try to discuss your code,
actually understand what is being written before you just put a pull request.
There's still a little bit of a standard there and be open to respond to feedback.
If you're going to try to,
you know, add code to a code base, expect it to be a little bit of pushback.
Try to learn something and try to be able to actually explain the decision
behind that code.
So the future is really moving towards collaboration.
It's not just humans, it's not just agents.
It's really a blend of the two, and that's where things are going.
So there still needs to be trust.
We still kind of need. And that's what vouch tries to do. Right.
Try to have some trust.
I still use AI to generate code, but there's always got to be the intent there
and understanding on still on the system while you're making those decisions
and then structure.
So try to add these agent skills context files
so that things can scale through humans and and bots
and then respect.
I think open source has always been on respect.
And that's becoming even more crucial now that it's so easy to generate code,
kind of be patient with maintainers, explain yourself.
And that's the biggest thing.
So what would I would take away from this is update your contributing files.
Normally you would put how for humans to actually go ahead and interact
with your code.
I would actually add a section to look on.
What is your contribution guidelines for agents or for AI.
This will actually also weed out.
Some agents will actually see this and be like, hey, I can't do this.
Not really.
They don't follow instructions that well yet,
but it is kind of good to have that written down.
And like we said, check in the files and check in the context files
and skills into your
and check in context files that aren't
just for the tools you're using, but also that the global ones like agents,
so that people who are using other tools, there's
so many different tools out there can also benefit from it,
and then add automation to protect your own time.
If there's going to be automation through these bots and through all these agents,
automate some of the easy stuff away, like that stale PR stuff we looked at,
as well as PR reviews and things like that.
And that's it.
Thank you very much.
Thank you so much, Jack.
Yeah we do.
We have a few minutes, very well timed.
We have a few minutes for questions.
Would anyone like to ask Jack a question?
Excellent.
Great presentation.
Thank you.
I noticed like all the tools to try to prevent people to commit slop.
But what is what is responsibility on the team like response time
or how long it takes for the team to react to when someone send a proper,
you know, if you have all these blockers, I want to to how people feel
when you are blocking all the potential, you know, like slop coming in
just to understand the reality of how you handle all the contributions.
Yeah, for sure.
I think it's a little bit of like a judgment call,
like most of these automations are to filter out the bad ones so that
your time as a maintainer can be spent on the ones that are actually high quality.
It's really just a filtering system
to take out the bad ones so that you're still, as a maintainer,
hopefully still having response times that are good to high
quality and ones that are still humans on the other end.
So I think it
yeah, it's a bit of a judgment call, but I think also having those like stated,
what kind of helps a lot to
so just having it clear guidelines or in the repository being like hey expect
two day turnaround time or I think we have that written down in our code base,
kind of what we strive for and just having it.
So there's kind of
someone putting up a pull request knows kind of the timeline as well.
So since you, you know, involve a lot of open source projects
and I'm developing a bunch of open source to I was seeing an evolution of
I was evolved commercial models where there is
more money, there's more business models around for simple support.
Right?
Because at the end of the day, it's SLA like the question was asking, right?
You know, the way the developer should not be working for free, right?
In that sense, right?
They're sharing the code, but they should not be.
There should be or they should be able to hire people to help.
For example, are you seeing the evolution of those commercial models
where the the users of open source have easier ways to pay
is not just contributions or donations, which doesn't really scale?
Yeah, I think one of the biggest ones for us to in open
source is like trying to realize when you see, because it is hard,
you know, open source used to be the place where, you know,
I would always recommend people to go try to learn coding, right?
Like, hey, find something you're passionate about,
go try to put up a pull request, kind of get some experience first.
Kind of like resume builder.
I think the important thing is to still try to find that
in the weeds there where like there is still a bit from our side
where we try to grow when we see there is someone actively kind of,
participating and not just saying, oh, that's bad code.
Like it kind of is a judgment call, right?
You want to keep keep to have that community aspect to it.
Sorry, but I was kind of talking more of I
you seeing companies paying for that level of support.
I haven't seen that.
Like everything we do is through GitHub and like there's not like a fast pass
or like a obviously if there's like some kind of
you don't get pinged being like, hey, you got to check out this issue.
We treat it all the same.
That's kind of why you're asking is like.
You don't, you don't.
It's not your problem because you have enough people that you pay to do on it.
But on the smaller open source project. Right.
Or the companies want to build business models around open source?
Yeah. I feel like.
It's similar to the last question.
It's like putting putting guidelines on what your response times
are going to be and then trying to stick to those and like
you can maybe it is setting up automation to try to help you like,
hey ping you, this one's about to hit the slow or SLA.
Yeah. Thank you.
Very interesting topic for sure.
So thank you for for that.
I understand why you're pushing back all these requests,
because now it's very easy for everyone to create a pull request and so on.
But rather than filtering and pushing back, wouldn't
it be better to kind of educate back rather than pushing back?
Because one of the the fears that we have as an industry
is who is going to teach
all these junior developers, mead, mead developers and so on.
And it kind of the industry is kind of leaning towards
who knows who, who knows what the good looks looks like.
And they are using the AI agents very well.
But we also need to use AI agents to,
to educate all the new engineers.
Otherwise.
I think it's like I think that's probably not just an open source related question.
Like that's for like everyone.
Like what does junior software engineering look like?
There's like people are moving to more towards agents.
And I think there's still like a mentoring aspect that is huge in that.
And I would say everyone here
like find the time to be purposeful with like mentoring others.
I know we have we have, we have like we have Summer of code programs
where we will take on like students throughout the summer in open source.
That's an open source program. It's not just a Google thing.
So like take on, take on juniors
and actually be thoughtful with like but it's evolving, right?
So it's like teaching them how to prompt better how to do the like.
I think it's also teaching them how to use the tools as well.
But we also do like code reviews and stuff. Like that.
I think all of us, we need to to do some part on it.
But I think from, from your perspective, maybe just not just pushing back,
but also kind of advising back how they they can create those requests
better because, yeah, all of us, we need to contribute on it.
Exactly. I think agent skills do play a part in that too.
Like that's why
we have those PR creator skills so that like hopefully does raise the bar
for somebody trying to contribute to projects and stuff like that.
On on the agent skills.
And I'll very shortly.
Yes.
It's good to to insert them in the into the repository.
But at some point because especially the skills
take the context, how they manage which one to put in their posture
and which one
not to put into their posture, because the context becomes too large for
for the AI assistant to get it the right way and to choose the right skill.
Yeah, we we try to save for, for for us it's like, what would you use
over 50% of the time?
Like, and that's kind of the number that we use to gate
what's disabled or enabled by default.
So like things like pull requests, it's like
you need that skill to put up to put it up code review as well.
So like the major ones, otherwise
we usually just put those as like slash commands or rules or.
Yeah.
But it has a great conversation with people
working on some of the new features to help maintainers in this new AI world.
So if you want to have a conversation, any of you
got good ideas, I mean, direct compensation from the slack,
because I ask you and the others involved in those technical features
like deleting pull requests and things like that.
Awesome. Ask people to get it back.
All right. Perfect. I'll see you.
Wow. Sniped excellent, guys.
You missed Jack's talk. What were you doing?
I'm so confused.
Thank you so much, Jack. That was excellent, everyone.
Thank you.
Amazing.